A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Reproductive Health and Population (RHP), Office Files of Margaret Hempel and Jose Barzelatto FA614
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Reproductive Health and Population (RHP), Office Files of Margaret Hempel and Jose Barzelatto
1965-1995, bulk 1991-1995
1991-1995
Rockefeller Archive Center
Hempel, Margaret
Barzelatto, Jose
Ford Foundation
FA614
4.8 Cubic Feet
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement
Arranged in 3 series by file type.
Scope and Contents
Contains correspondence, trip files and subject files.
Biographical / Historical
Margaret Hempel is a foundation executive who worked at the Ford Foundation during two different spans of time. She initially joined the Foundation as an Assistant Program Officer in its Urban Poverty Program before moving to its Reproductive Health and Population Program (RHP) in 1990 as an Assistant Program Officer. She was then promoted to Program Officer and then Deputy Director until a change in the Foundation's programming converted RHP to the Human Development and Reproductive Health unit (HDRH) of the Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS) in 1996. From then until she left the Foundation in 1999, she served as a Deputy Director of HDRH. Hempel later returned to the Foundation as Director of the Gender, Racial, and Ethnic Justice Program.
In between her two different stints at the Ford Foundation, Hempel served as Vice President for Programs at the American Jewish World Service and Vice President for Programs at the Ms. Foundation for Women. She became a Consultant for the Girls First Fund after her second time at the Ford Foundation.
Hempel earned a B.A. from John Hopkins University and an M.A. from Princeton University.
Biographical / Historical
Jose Barzelatto (1926-2006) was an endocrinologist, nuclear medicine physician, foundation executive, and reproductive and sexual health advocate who worked for several years at the Ford Foundation. Barzelatto initially started as a Senior Program Advisor at the Urban Poverty Program and then became Director of the Reproductive Health and Population Program (RHP).
Prior to joining the Ford Foundation, Barzelatto had positions as a professor of medicine at the University of Chile and as Director of the Special Program of Research, Development, and Research Training at the World Health Organization (WHO). After leaving the Foundation, he became Vice President of the Center for Health and Social Policy.
- Chronological Correspondence, 1991-1995; I
  - Outgoing Cables and General Correspondence, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - Hempel Chronological Correspondence, A-C, 1993 January-September (Box 1)
  - Hempel Chronological Correspondence, D-H, 1993 January-September (Box 1)
  - Hempel Chronological Correspondence, I-O, 1993 January-September (Box 1)
  - Hempel Chronological Correspondence, P-W, 1993 January-September (Box 1)
  - Hempel Chronological Correspondence, X-Z, 1993 January-September (Box 1)
  - Hempel Chronological Correspondence, A-Z, 1993 October-December (Box 1)
  - Marjorie Muecke Chronological Correspondence, A-R, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Marjorie Muecke Chronological Correspondence, S-Z, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Barzelatto Chronological Correspondence, A-Z, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Hempel Chronological Correspondence, A-Z, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Marjorie Muecke Chronological Correspondence, A-Z, 1994 (Box 2)
  - Hempel Chronological Correspondence, A-Z, 1995 (Box 2)
  - Marjorie Muecke Chronological Correspondence, A-M, 1995 (Box 2)
  - Marjorie Muecke Chronological Correspondence, N-Z, 1995 (Box 2)
- Jose Barzelatto Trip Files, 1990-1995; II
  - Field Office Visits in Manila; Evaluate Reproductive Health Activities in Jakarta, 1990 January 1-February 3 (Box 2)
  - Plenary Session Statement by Jose Barzelatto (unnamed conference), 1990 February 22 (Box 2)
  - Anubhav Workshop (Goa, India), 1990 April 13-20 (Box 2)
  - Reproductive Rights -- Visits to Grantees in Cairo and Occupied Territories (Cairo, Egypt; Jerusalem, Israel), 1990 May 12-18 (Box 2)
  - Operations Research on Family Planning (Columbia, Maryland) and Johns Hopkins University Visit with Henry Mosley (Baltimore, Maryland), 1990 June 11-13 (Box 2)
  - Safe Motherhood Initiative (Geneva, Switzerland), 1990 June 19-20 (Box 2)
  - Reproductive Health Technologies Project (Washington, DC), 1990 July 8-9 (Box 2)
  - Family Health International -- TAC Meeting (Durham, North Carolina), 1990 July 19 (Box 2)
  - Interagency Meeting on Reproductive Health (Geneva, Switzerland), 1990 September 11-14 (Box 2)
  - "From Abortion to Contraception" -- World Health Organization (Tbilisi), 1990 October 10-13 (Box 2)
  - International Forum for AIDS Research (IFAR), 1990 October 31 (Box 2)
  - 6th International Women's Health Meeting (Manila, Philippines; Margaret Hempel only), 1990 November 3-9 (Box 2)
  - "The Beginning of Human Life" -- University of Iowa, 1990 November 4-7 (Box 2)
  - Johns Hopkins Workshop Re: Women's and Children's Health (Cairo, Egypt), 1990 December 2-4 (Box 3)
  - Reproductive Health Program Officers Meeting (Tarrytown, New York), 1990 December 5-7 (Box 3)
  - Mombasa, Manila, Bombay -- INCLEN -- HR -- Tata University, 1991 January 20-February 12 (Box 3)
  - Mexico and San Francisco, California, 1991 (Box 3)
  - Mexico, San Francisco, Nairobi, Harare, 1991 February 25-March 14 (Box 3)
  - Caribbean, Chile, Brazil, 1991 April 8-26 (Box 3)
  - Jakarta, Manila, Bangkok, Geneva, 1991 June 5-22 (Box 3)
  - NCIH 18th Annual International Health Conference -- Conference Planning (Arlington, Virginia), 1991 June 23-26 (Box 3)
  - Beijing, 1991 August (Box 3)
  - Bangladesh/Senegal -- Conference on Antiprogestin Drugs, 1991 October (Box 3)
  - New Delhi, Bombay, 1991 November (Box 3)
  - Human Rights and Governance Staff Meeting (Manila, Philippines), 1991 November 18-23 (Box 3)
  - Anti-Progestins Meeting -- Society of Law and Medicine (Arlington, Virginia), 1991 December 6-7 (Box 3)
  - New York -- Completed Meetings, 1991 (Box 3)
  - International Union for the Scientific Study of Population (IUSSP) Meeting (Rome, Italy), 1992 January 25-February 4 (Box 3)
  - World Bank/World Health Organization -- "Effective Family Planning" (London, England), 1992 February 4-6 (Box 3)
  - Reproductive Health Program Review, 1992 February 14 (Box 3)
  - Rockefeller Foundation Meeting (Washington, DC), 1992 February 26-28 (Box 3)
  - Bellagio (Milan) Meeting; Orlando, Florida; Washington, DC, 1992 March (Box 3)
  - Asia Reproductive Health Meeting (Delhi), 1992 March 14-22 (Box 3)
  - Board of Trustees Meeting, 1992 March 25-26 (Box 3)
  - Summit Hotel/IUD Meeting (New York, New York), 1992 March 27-28 (Box 3)
  - Santiago, Chile -- Visit to Grantees and Field Office, 1992 April 6-12 (Box 3)
  - Council on Foundations 43 Annual Conference (Miami, Florida), 1992 April 27-29 (Box 3)
  - Program Reviews (Ford Foundation, New York, New York), 1992 May 4-15 (Box 3)
  - June 2nd Activities -- Seminar on Diversity and Staff Photograph, 1992 June 2 (Box 3)
  - Family Health International Technical Advisory Committee Annual Meeting (Barzelatto not in attendance), 1992 July 1-2 (Box 3)
  - American Society of Law and Medicine, Third International Conference (Toronto, Canada), 1992 July 19-23 (Box 3)
  - 12th International Conference on Social Sciences and Medicine (Edinburgh, Scotland), 1992 September (Box 3)
  - "Meeting Women's Needs for Post-Abortion Family Planning" (Bellagio, Italy), 1993 February 1-5 (Box 3)
  - Paris, 1993 February 7-10 (Box 3)
  - Pan American Health Organization (El Paso, Texas), 1993 February 17-19 (Box 3)
  - RHP Program Review, 1993 March 5 (Box 3)
  - International Symposium on Contraceptive Research and Development for the Year 2000 and Beyond and Meeting on Human Reproduction Research (Mexico City, Mexico), 1993 March 8-11 (Box 3)
  - Program Review and Joint Program Reviews, 1993 March-April (Box 3)
  - John Havard and Marianne Haselgrave Meeting with Jose Barzelatto in New York, 1993 March 24 (Box 3)
  - Board of Trustees Meeting, 1993 March 24-25 (Box 3)
  - Council on Foundations 44th Annual Conference -- Background Material, 1993 April (Box 3)
  - Santiago, Chile and Argentina, 1993 May (Box 3)
  - Board of Trustees Meeting, 1993 June 23-25 (Box 3)
  - Technical Advisory Committee Annual Meeting (North Carolina), 1993 June 30-July 1 (Box 3)
  - Public Conversations Project (Massachusetts), 1993 July 16 (Box 3)
  - Jay Satia Paper and Meeting, 1993 September 21 (Box 3)
  - Canada and India, 1993 October 17-31 (Box 3)
  - Population Donor/ICPD Meeting (Ford Foundation, New York, New York), 1993 November 16 (Box 3)
  - American Anthropological Association Annual Meeting (Washington, DC), 1993 November 17-21 (Box 3)
  - December Meetings, 1993 December (Box 3)
  - Population Council (Cairo, Egypt), 1994 February (Box 4)
  - International Health Seminar Series, "Issues in Reproductive Health" (University of Minnesota), 1994 May 13 (Box 4)
  - "Finding Common Ground" Policy Conference (Columbia University), 1994 May 17 (Box 4)
  - Social Science Research Council, Sexuality Report Meetings, 1994 October 5-6 (Box 4)
  - Abortion Meeting (Bogota and Peru), 1994 November 10-27 (Box 4)
  - Common Security Forum (Harvard University), 1994 December 4-7 (Box 4)
  - Education and Culture Workshop (Bamako, Mali, West Africa), 1995 January 15-20 (Box 4)
  - Population Council, 1995 February 6-7 (Box 4)
  - Gertrude Mongella Meeting, 1995 March 1 (Box 4)
  - Reuter Forum (Columbia University), 1995 April 19 (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees Meeting, 1995 June (Box 4)
  - Donor Workshop on Implementing Reproductive Health Programs, 1995 June 12-14 (Box 4)
  - World Health Organization, Policy and Coordination Committee Meetings, 1995 June 16-25 (Box 4)
  - Mexico-Santiago, 1995 June 30-July 17 (Box 4)
  - Mexico City-Orlando, 1995 August (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees Meeting, 1995 September (Box 4)
  - Working Group on Reproductive Health and Family Planning, 1995 October 2 (Box 4)
  - Bethesda, Maryland-Budapest, Hungary, 1995 October (Box 4)
  - International Forum for Social Sciences and Health (IFSSH) Workshop (Canada), 1995 October 15-22 (Box 4)
  - Geneva-Jerusalem-London, 1995 October 31-November 7 (Box 4)
  - Foundation Officers Gathering (Chicago, Illinois), 1995 November 29 (Box 4)
  - London, 1995 December 4-5 (Box 4)
- Subject Files, 1965-1993; III
  - Mexico Population Program -- Program Discussion Paper by James W. Trowbridge, 1965 October (Box 4)
  - Sexuality Committee Group -- Agenda 1/4/93 Meeting, 1993 January 4 (Box 4)
  - Sexuality Committee Group -- Original Invite Letters Re: Jan 4 Meeting, 1993 January 4 (Box 4)
  - Sexuality Committee Group -- Job Description and Population Research Workshop, 1993 February 8-9 (Box 4)
  - Sexuality Committee Group -- Potential Advisors, 1992-1993 (Box 4)
  - Sexuality Committee Group -- Notes, Letters, Memoranda, etc., 1992-1993 (Box 4)